Guide to the Fred Schofs Papers ALBA.056
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Fred Schofs Papers
1939-1975
bulk
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Kolbe, Ulrich
Schofs, Fred, 1910-1975
ALBA.056
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
Gottfried Jakob (Fred) Schofs (1910-1975) was a leftist German national who went to the U.S. in 1928 and lived there as an illegal alien. He volunteered for Spain in 1937, and served as a Mess Sergeant for the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. He also took part in the battles of Brunete, Quinto, Belchite, Fuentes de Ebro and Teruel, and was wounded twice. At the end of the war he was incarcerated in several camps in France, and in december 1943 escaped back into Spain, where he spent more than two years in a camp at Miranda del Ebro. After World War II he settled in West Germany where he was a union organizer and political activist. The collection includes his resume (in German), a questionnaire of the West German Spanish Civil War veterans' organization, Letters from authorities in the U.S. and France relating to his return to the U.S., passports from the 1940s through the 1970s, correspondence, journal entries written from Miranda del Ebro, and various VALB publications. Also included is his Hans Beimler Medal awarded by the German Democratic Republic in 1956.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically.
Historical/Biographical Note
Gottfried Jakob (Fred) Schofs was born on August 28, 1910 at München-Gladbach, Germany, the eldest of seven children. His parents were Jakob and Anna Schofs. His father was a socialist and initiated his son into politics. Schofs entered the Sozialistische Arbeiterjugend (SAJ = Young Socialist Workers) in 1926. He left Germany for the United States in 1928. He attended evening school at Philadelphia and worked as a cook in hotels and restaurants. After working briefly at the Abraham Lincoln Hotel in Reading, PA, he became a cook in at the Esplanade Hotel, New York City, in 1937. A member of the Communist Party USA, of the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union, and of the American League against War and Fascism (later American League for Peace and Democracy), he decided to join the American volunteers leaving for Spain. His decision was made stronger by the fact that his father, still in Germany, had been sent to a camp.
Schofs crossed the French border through the Pyrenees and entered Spain on April 19, 1937. Working as a cook, he was promoted to Mess Sergeant on November 24, 1937. He also took part of the battles of Brunete, Aragon, Teruel and the Ebro offensive. He was wounded twice, the first time on May 10, 1938, the second time on October 20, 1938, both times from artillery barrage. He was injured in the head and arms. Staying on active duty until the retreat of the International Brigades, he left Spain in 1939. As he arrived in France he was arrested by the French police and sent to camp Saint-Cyprien from February 9, 1939 until the end of March 1939. Freed, he then worked as secretary of the Abraham Lincoln Committee at Le Havre. He was arrested again and sent back to a camp, first in Varimpre, then briefly near Lisieux, and finally near Bordeaux, from October 1939 until June 20, 1940. At that time, facing the advance of the German army, the authorities of the camp decided to free all the political refugees. Leaving Bordeaux, he went to Perpignan and worked at the prefecture, at the Service technique des camps, managing to elude the Gestapo. From time of the occupation of the south of France in November, 1942, he became involved in the French underground and took part in sabotage actions against the German army, along with two other International Brigades veterans. They were racked by the Gestapo, and Schofs was the only one of the three who escaped the arrest, fleeing across the border to Spain on December 6, 1943. Caught by the Spanish police on December 8th, he was sent to prison, first in Gerona, then in Saragossa, finally in Barcelona, and was eventually put in the Miranda de Ebro camp on January 11, 1944.
As a prisoner there for more than two years, worked as a cook for the camp. Along with other German former International Brigaders and anti-fascists, he published a newspaper, Deutsche Nachrichten (German News) and tried to organize political discussions. The group was turned over to the Guardia Civil by other prisoners. Four prisoners of the camp who had fought with the Spanish Republic were sent to a prison in Madrid in February 1945. They eventually were freed, the last two in the spring of 1946. From December 1943, Schofs corresponded intensively with various authorities, trying to find a way out of Spain. At first, pretending to be an American citizen, he discussed with the American consulate in Spain a possible return to the United States. He had already made several applications to U.S. authorities since 1939. But the only result he got was receiving material aid from the Representation in Spain of the American Relief Organizations.
By the end of summer 1944 Schofs had almost given up on returning to the U.S., and tried instead to get a visa to France. Yet, he remained unsuccessful until the end of 1945, when he decided to ask for a temporary stay in France, as first step toward a return to West Germany. He finally obtained his visa to France on January 21, 1946 and crossed the Spanish border on January 24th. He arrived at Frankfurt-am-Main on April 8, 1946, and lived there until his death in 1975.
He was a member of the VVN (Vereinigung der Verfolgten des Nazisregimes = Union of Persecuted of the Nazi Regime) and was active in the Communist Party, Hessen, first as an adviser and then as an instructor. He traveled regularly to East Germany and Spain. He married Vicencia in 1967, and served as secretary of the German veterans of the Spanish Civil War until weakened by heart disease in his later years. A lifelong trade-unionist, he belonged to the ÖTV (Union of public Services Employees and Transport Employees) and later to the Union for Textile Employees in West Germany.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Scope and Contents
The major part of the collection consists of correspondence written by or addressed to Fred Schofs, dated between 1940 and 1946. It reveals Schofs' attempts to get out of the Miranda de Ebro Camp, contacting various authorities, American and French, and former International Brigaders; correspondents include Peter Rhodes and Aurelio Vila. In the letters, Schofs tells the story of his life, and explains his current situation. The collection also includes Schofs' identification papers from United States, France and Germany. One document, a draft of a speech he gave in 1972 at a gathering of the German Communist Party, on behalf of the Veterans of the Party, relates his political motivations and choices throughout his life. Finally, a few documents testify about life in the camp in Spain: examples are a hand illustrated menu for Christmas 1944, and three typescripts related to the denunciation of Schofs and his group’s political activities (a list of the prisoners who took part in the denunciation, a copy of the text of the denunciation itself, and a list of other German prisoners in the Miranda de Ebro Camp). Schofs’ Hans Beimler Medal (GDR) for German Veterans of the Spanish Civil War is present in the collection, along with a certificate related to it.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Ulrich Kolbe and Frank Dittmeyer in 2002. The accession number associated with this gift is 2002.041.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Prisoners and prisons.; Documents.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Identity cards.; Anti-fascist movements |z Germany.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- International brigades.; Kolbe, Ulrich; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Speidel, Hans, 1897-1984; Schofs, Fred, 1910-1975
- Correspondence, Sep 4, 1940-Mar 21, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, Dec 15, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, Feb 2, 1944-Apr 25, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, May 8, 1944-Aug 30, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, Sep 3, 1944-Dec 26, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, Jan 2, 1945-Jun 22, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, Jul 5, 1945-Aug 20, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, Sep 3, 1945-Dec 21, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, Jan 12, 1946-Mar 7, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, undated; [Jan 11, 1944-Mar 31, 1944?] (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Documents: Communist Party, West Germany, [1946?] / 1970-Aug 28, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Documents: Honors, Germany, [Jul 18, 1956-1975] (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Documents: Identification Papers, France, Feb 28, 1946-Feb 19, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Documents: Identification Papers, Germany, Apr 8, 1946-Apr 18, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Documents: Identification Papers, USA, May, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Documents: Miranda de Ebro, Life in the Camp, Dec 25, 1944-Jan 26, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Former German Volunteers in Spanish Civil War Committee: Form, Fred Schofs, Aug 4, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Hans Beimler Medal: Certificate and Medal, in Cases, Jul 18, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Hans Speidel Case: Clippings, Mar 1957-[Apr?] 1957 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Notebook: Fred Schofs (Article Translations, 1942; Accounts, 1943), 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Obituary: Fred Schofs, Dec, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Spain: Communist Party, Clippings, Jan, 1972-Mar 13, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Spanish Civil War: Clippings, Jun, 1946-1967 (Box 1, Folder 23)